Finding aid for Manuel Luis Quezon papers, 1909-1944
Bentley Historical Library
- General Correspondence, 1909-1944; 21 reels
  - President of the Senate
    - April 1, 1919-January 5, 1921 (Reel 9)
      Highlights of roll 9, April 1, 1919-January 5, 1921, with comments and notes by Michael Cullinane:
      Erwin Winslow--greatly decreased
      Camilo Osias--occasional, mostly re: Philippine independence activities
      George Malcolm
      J. de Veyra and Yangco (Resident Commissioner)--mostly re: business, "coastline laws", independence issue, continual advice being given by Quezon
      I. Gabaldon (later joins de Veyra as Resident Commissioner)
      E. Aguinaldo (Oct. 27, 1919)
      Manuel Quiogue (Officer of Census) esp. 5 page letter (July 10, 1920) re: a complaint filed with Quezon presumably involving Julio de la Rosa
      Sergio Osmeña--somewhat reduced in number, include one instance of a near rift between them:
      Quezon to Osmeña (from Washington). Cable (April 3, 1919) with Quezon complaining that his advice is no longer being heeded as before
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (April 5, 1919) Osmeña denies it, suggests it must be Quezon's bad health that causes his unexplainable behavior, he expresses ignorance of Quezon's motives
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (April 5, 1919) re: a confusion in their communication procedure, which explains Osmeña's confusion about Quezon's motives, etc.--recommends a more efficient system of citing cablegrams
    - January 6, 1921-May 24, 1922 (Reel 10)
      Highlights of roll 10, January 6, 1921-May 24, 1922, with notes and comments by Michael Cullinane:
      James A. Frear (Pro-Filipino, U.S. Representative)
      Judge Horace M. Towner (U.S. Representative)
      F. M. McIntyre
      General J. Harbord--containing personal correspondence
      James J. Rafferty (Philippine Commercial Agent, S.F.) --mostly re: the status of Filipinos in the U.S.
      F.B.Harrison, esp. Harrison to Quezon letter (Nov. 7, 1921) re: (in part) D. Barrows
      General H. H. Bandholtz, Quezon met with him in Washington
      Charles E. Russell, author and publisher (journalist?)
      J. de Veyra (Resid. Comm.) quite heavy, much re: selection of Governor-General and Wood
      de Veyra to Quezon and Osmeña. 5 page letter (Jan. 15, 1921)
      Osmeña and Quezon to de Veyra. Cable (Jan. 18, 1921) re: evaluation of Wood, generally opposed to his "military" character, contends "people" will react negatively to this aspect of Wood, as like in Spanish days
      de Veyra to Osmeña. Cable (Jan. 20, 1921) re: Wood: "Believe, however, that the objective to his candidacy is more apparent than real..."; warns that the choice could be worse
      de Veyra to Osmeña and Quezon. 4 page letter (Feb. 15, 1921) re: Wood plus four letters that de Veyra sent to Wood (February, early April, 1921)
      de Veyra to Osmeña and Quezon. Cable (Feb. 25, 1921) Re: Wood "...knowing his simplicity, sincerity and uprightness I can draw nothing from his attitude but a spirit of good will towards us and our aspirations." (written after a meeting de Veyra had with Wood)
      correspondence re: Wood continues, with also heavy correspondence re: Wood-Forbes Mission--through 1921-1922
      de Veyra to Quezon. Letters (during June, 1921) re: various attacks against Quezon in U.S. due to his alleged contradictory public and private position re: Philippine independence and also the changing mood in U.S.
      Osmeña to de Veyra. Cable (Aug. 3, 1921) Osmeña recommends N. Romualdez (Leyte) to be chief justice, Philippine Supreme Court (again on Aug.6, 1921) --gives praise
      Osmeña to de Veyra. Cable (Aug. 11, 1921) "to avoid further complications" Osmeña received the immediate appointment of Arraullo to be chief justice-can't get Romualdez
      Isauro Gabaldon (Resident Commissioner) esp:
      Gabaldon to Quezon. Cable (Jan. 13, 1922) re: Quezon break with Osmeña
      Quezon to Gabaldon. Cable (Jan. 23, 1922) Quezon's reply on above
      F. Buencamino, esp. 3 page letter to "My Dear Casey" re: his suggestions for new Philippines
      R. Palma. Letter (Nov. 9, 1921) from Quezon--re: political situation
      T. Sandiko (Letter to F. B. Harrison--Feb. 8, 1921) plus note written on it to Quezon, compelling Quezon to look with favor upon Sandiko's resolution re: electoral Law-- thus Sandiko's letter plus Harrison's comment forwarded to Quezon
      Henry D. Woolfe. (Letter to Quezon, April 21, 1922--re: complaints)
      Mariano R. Marcos (Ladag, Ilocos Sur) re: general conditions in his province in election (April 8, 1922)
      R. Montinola--mostly re: getting him to defect to Coleonvistas, esp.
      J. Ross to R. M. 4 page letter (Jan. 25, 1922) Ross praises Quezon, suggest R.M. get together with him
      R. M. to J. Ross. Letter (Jan. 31, 1922) R. M.'s response, guarded compliance
      R. M. to Quezon. Letter (Feb. 21, 1922) re: advice to Quezon on Negros politics
      R. M. to Quezon. Letter (Feb. 21, 1922) re: Iloilo politics, esp. Yulo to Roxas to Osmeña
      E. Finley Johnson (Associate Justice, Philippine Supreme Court). 2 page letter from Quezon (April 23, 1921) re: Harrison's favoring Nacionalistas, a reply to Johnson
      E. Tirona (Pres. Gen, P. Democrata), esp:
      E. T. to Osmeña. 2 page letter (April 30, 1921) re: Democrata real desire for independence
      Osmeña to E. T. 3 page letter (May 3, 1921) re: Nacionalistas policy, suggests a joint petition to the Wood-Forbes mission
      E. T. to Osmeña. Letter (May 4, 1921) re: their mutual desire to form a joint petition, suggests going ahead with it
      Elpidio Quirino, esp.:
      "Memorandum for the President of the Colect. Party" (March 22, 1922)--to Quezon re: his candidacy in Ilocos Sur and some Colectivista problems in that province
      "Memorandum for Mr. E. Quirino"(March 22, 1922)--from Quezon in response to E. Quirino, also re: strategy in Ilocos Sur and Colectivista action there
      [unsigned?) Letter to Quezon (in Tagalog, the first one in the General Correspondence) (March 9, 1921) re: the writers strong desire for Filipino freedom, the Wood-Forbes, a brief review of American period, and he concludes with: "Nais ko pong makita ans ating Kalayaan."
    - June 8, 1922-June 27, 1925 (Reel 11)
      Highlights of roll 11, June 8, 1922-June 27, 1925, with notes and comments by Michael Cullinane:
      Harold M. Pitt (Oakland, California) --business
      General H. H. Bandholtz? --mostly all personal
      Clyde H. Tavenner (editor and publisher of The Philippine Reporter in U.S.)
      Jay Lovestone (Workers Party of America)
      Maximo M. Kalaw--studying and writing in U.S., re: mostly Philippine Party system
      Camilo Osias, esp.
      Four page letter to Quezon (June 15, 1922) re: political situation in Philippines
      Osias to Enage. Memorandum (June 23, 1922) re: his opposition to government funding of Aguinaldo's trip to U.S. (Spanish-American War Veterans Convention)--also refers to a dinner at P. Ostavera's house
      Enage--regular correspondence while Quezon in Washington
      Enage to Quezon. Cable (June 20, 1922) re: Manila politics, fusion with Democratas, notes: "...Gomez has already declared Colectivista in a banquet in Tacloban...", also expresses desire to get Isagelo de los Santes to affiliate with them
      Enage to Quezon. Cable (Sept. 23, 1924) re: again activities in Manila, report
      Isbelo de los Santos, esp: [from Ilocos Sur]
      Quezon to Santos (2 page letter), June 21, 1922, in which he moves to get his support
      Santos to Enage. Letter (June 24, 1922) re: favorable response to Quezon's letter
      Quezon to Santos. Letter (June 26, 1922) thanking him for affiliating [other correspondence explaining the role played by Bishop Aglipay in getting Santos to come]
      Manuel Quioque. 6 page memo to Quezon (June 24, 1922) re: election
      T. H. Pardo de Tavera. Letter from Quezon (June 26, 1922) re: Philippine and Manila politics
      Jaime C. de Veyra. 3 page letter to Quezon (July 23, 1922)--informing Quezon, who is returning to Manila, of political situation and also an article in La Vanguardia about Democrata victories (June 13) which Veyra believes was written by an important public figure, also briefly re: Wood's stand on the election
      T. Earnshaw. 5 page letter to Quezon (as "Chico"), Aug. 2, 1922 re: fusion, his opinion
      Fermin Torralba (Bohol). 2 page letter to Quezon (March 11, 1924) re: his loyalty to Quezon, but his opposition to Osmeña, thus again fusion
      E. Aguinaldo, mostly re: his mission to U.S. (March-April, 1924)
      Manuel Roxas, heavy correspondence with Quezon while Quezon and Osmeña were not yet in Washington--mostly re: Fairfield Bill--also heavy correspondence Washington to Manila from Quezon and Osmeña when they arrive in Washington
      I. Gabaldon. Cable from Quezon to Washington, (Nov. 28, 1924) re: Quezon's advice to Gabaldon to either return and campaign for representative or drop out of campaign in Nueva Ecija in order not to "expose yourself to a defeat"
      Vicente Bunuan, heavy correspondence with Quezon from Washington as head of Philippine Press. Letter, March 14, 1925, refers to reports in U.S. re: a class war going on in Nueva Ecija led by Colorums and Politices
      M. J. Cuenco (Cebu), esp. Cuenco to Roxas. 11 page letter (Dec. 6, 1922) re: Osmeña
      M. M. Kalaw, esp. Quezon to Kalaw. Letter (Nov. 19, 1923) re: Quezon negative reaction to Kalaw's attack on him for favoring Nacs. as appointees
      Roberto Alcantara (Democrata), esp. letter to Quezon (Nov. 22, 1923) re: his praise of Quezon for including opposition party members in his appointments
      S. Osmeña, esp. 2 page letter from Quezon (June 17, 1925) re: the arrangements of a mass triumphant rally and celebration in Manila including Osmeña, Quezon, Roxas, etc. Quezon laments that victorious Cebu legislators will not be coming for this, he advises that they change their plans and come earlier
      Governor-General Leonard Wood, esp:
      [unsigned] to Wood. 3 page letter (June 3, 1924) re: Quezon's work in Washington and progress of Fairfield Bill and setting a date for independence
      Quezon to Wood. Letter (July 3, 1923) re: a warning to him concerning the Filipino attitude toward him
      Quezon, Roxas, Laurel, et. al to Wood. Letters of resignation (July 17, 1923)
      Quezon to Wood. Letter (July 19, 1923) stressing the peaceful nature of their move, no need to call army or be alarmed
      Quezon to [Minamahal na Kababayan?]--brief letter in Tagalog by Quezon (Oct. 4, 1923) re: the running of Ramon Fernandez for Guevara's seat in Senate [1st letter in general correspondence written by Quezon in Tagalog]
    - July 3, 1925-February 11, 1928 (Reel 12)
      Highlights of roll 12, July 3, 1925-February 11, 1928, with notes and comments by Michael Cullinane:
      F. McIntyre, Moorfield Storey, Frank Carpenter, Carmi A. Thompson
      Secretary of War
      Governor-General Henry L. Stimson--heavy in late 1927, early 1928, much re: getting him settled in
      James Harbord and James Ross--continuing personal correspondence; Harbord to Secretary of War (Oct. 13, 1927) with lavish praise of Quezon
      W. H. Lawrence (Attorney, S.F. California)
      Many U.S. Congressmen, esp. Sen. William King and Sen. Burton Wheeler
      Jose Abad Santos (Philippine Press, Washington) "My Dear Joe"
      V. Bunuan (Philippine Press) re: independence issue and activities in Washington
      Pedro Guevara (Resid. Comm.) much re: reorganization of Filipino movement, and U.S. Congressional activities, etc.
      Clyde Tavenner (The Philippine Republic) esp.:
      C.T. to Recto. Letter (July 3, 1926) re: a very anti-Osmeña attack, esp. of Osmeña's "no agitation" policy, C.T. wants more radical moves
      Quezon to Tavenner. Letter (Dec. 15, 1927) re: removal of support from Philippine Republic and expressing animosity to C. T. for his threats, etc., breaking their friendship
      MacArthur, esp. letter from Quezon (Dec. 25, 1925), personal, but also re: sad condition in Philippines at time
      Benigno Aquino (Maj. Floor Leader, House)
      R. Palma
      James Ross, esp. letter from Quezon (Jan. 21, 1928) re: Stimson's settling in, stress that Mrs. Stimson "must be made to meet the right kind of American ladies in the Philippines" [i.e. Mrs. Ross and her friends]
      S. Osmeña (in Washington) esp:
      Letter to his legislative colleagues, 25 pages (Sept. 3, 1926) re: Washington activities
      Quezon to Osmeña. Cable (Nov. 3, 1925) re: selection of Resid. Comm.
      Osmeña to Quezon. Cable (Nov. 4, 1925) "regarding myself, leave matter entirely to you and party"
      E. T. Tirona, esp:
      Tirona [Gov.] Letter (July 22, 1926) re: planned demonstration to Thompson Mission
      Quezon to Tirona. Letter (July 29, 1926)
      Tirona to Quezon. Letter (Aug. 3, 1926) Quezon tells Tirona of Thomas Gumez (Democrata)'s seat in Senate vacant, Tirona tells Quezon Democrata will not be putting up candidate to fill it
      Leonard Wood, esp. Executive Order (Nov. 9, 1926) abolishing Board of Control
      Montinola (Gov. Iloilo) (Pres. Democratas), esp:
      Montinola to Quezon. Letter and enclosure (Feb. 21, 1927) re: suggestion unites front
      Quezon to Montinola. Letter (March 22, 1927)--most favorable reply
      Tomas Confesor (Representative, House), esp. letter to Quezon and reply by Quezon (early Nov., 1927) re: his split with Roxas, Quezon advises getting back together against opposition
      National Supreme Council, esp.:
      Quezon to N.S.C. (Sept. 22, 1926) re: effort and problem of getting a united Filipino stand on big issues, Quezon cautions: "...soy de opinion que el momento no permite que en la expresion de muestras aspiraliones se use de un lenguate que pueda dar lugar a una deble interpretacion."
      Committee of Independence, esp. letter of Quezon to Committee (Sept. 26, 1926) re: reactivation of its activities and work for Filipino independence
      Maximo Kalaw, esp.:
      Quezon to Kalaw. 3 page letter (Sept. 20, 1927) re: Kalaw's joint stand with Sumulong on Independence Fund Drive, opposed to it, Quezon explains his side
      Kalaw to Quezon. 3 page letter (Sept. 26, 1927) re: a frank refutation of Quezon's argument, says he'll publish more articles re: Filipino parties, esp. Filipino party system
      Manuel Roxas, esp:
      Roxas to Quezon. 4 page letter (May 27, 1927) re: a political description of politics on Capiz and Nacionalista power there, also Ledesma's power
      Roxas to Quezon. Cable (June 22-23, 1927) re: successful election results Capiz, Romblon, and Cebu
      Quezon to Roxas. Letter (Jan. 23, 1928) re: Stimson's settling in "...try to have our people meet the Stimson's socially. You notice he will make it a point to be in touch with us. Have Trining [Mrs. Roxas] and her friends call on Mrs. Stimson."
      Quezon to Roxas. Cable (Feb. 1, 1928) re: Stimson socially: "Unlike Wood, he and wife desire to have social intercourse with our people and we should give them opportunity."
      [Some correspondence in 1927-28, after Wood's death to get a favorable Governor-General and achieve, "harmony" in government. --Quezon's first choice is McIntyre but is happy with Stimson]
    - February 11, 1928-December 14, 1929 (Reel 13)
      Highlights of roll 13, February 11, 1928-December 14, 1929, with notes and comments by Michael Cullinane:
      J. Ross, F. McIntyre, J. Harbord--continuing correspondence
      N. Roosevelt (New York Times)--Quezon takes exception with one of his articles
      V. Bunuan (Philippine Press--heavy correspondence)
      P. Guevara and I. Gabaldon--mostly re: tactics in U.S. Congress
      Guevara to Quezon. Letter (April 17, 1928) re: the controversy caused by Garaldon upon his return to Manila
      Many U.S. Congressmen re: independence issue, campaign in the U.S.
      Henry Stimson (after his departure from Philippines), esp:
      Stimson to Quezon. Letter (March 3, 1929) re: controversy over Judge Opisso (Capiz); Henry Stimson favors his promotion in judiciary system, informs Quezon
      Quezon to Stimson. Letter (June 9, 1929)--Quezon examines opposition to Opisso, late reply
      Stimson to Quezon. 4 page letter (July 31, 1929)--gives his case for Opisso, notes that this matter is the "only subject" on which they have disagreed
      M. Roxas, esp. letter from Quezon (April 12, 1929) re: judiciary appointments and inner Nacionalista Party feuds, esp. in 2nd district Luzon election, about who is to be speaker pro tem.
      Henry Stimson
      Philippine Sugar Association--considerable correspondence re: sugar negotiations
      Rafael Alunan (Secretary of Agriculture and National Resources)--also to Washington
      Maximo Kalaw--mostly re: K's attacks on Quezon for work on Jones Bill
      Manuel Roxas, esp.:
      Roxas to Quezon. Cable (April 14, 1928) "Gabaldon arrived making statements attacking you, Osmeña, for disloyalty immediate independence laws and cooperation with Stimson, stating further: "In America, they worked only for their personal interests, while I struggled for those of our people." "If there has been treason, they have committed it." Strong statement from you necessary
      Quezon to Roxas. Cable (April 14, 1928) "Not care to answer Gabaldon. Osmeña can do it. His attack is my deserved punishment for having supported a useless public official." See also Quezon to Gabaldon letter (April, 1928)
      Louis J. van Schaick, esp.: letter to Quezon plus enclosures (June 5, 1929) re: his memoirs of Quezon
      "Memorandum Para El Senador Osmeña" by Quezon (Sept. 20, 1929) re: the disposition of their official correspondence re: the early campaign in Washington about Jones Bill
      MacArthur, Douglas esp:
      MacArthur to Quezon. Letter (March 29, 1929) re: Quezon's and MacArthur's efforts to make MacArthur the new Governor-General after Stimson, a mutual desire
      MacArthur to Quezon. Letter (April 30, 1929) re: above [apparently this whole plan is unknown to Osmeña and Roxas who are in Washington, seemingly working to keep all military people out of Governor-Generalship--their correspondence to Quezon stress Filipino opposition to military pro-consul]
      MacArthur to Quezon. Letter (May 16, 1929) thanking Quezon for his efforts and his loyalty in his behalf, i.e. to get MacArthur into Governor-Generalship
    - December 16, 1929-July 24, 1931 (Reel 14)
      Highlights of roll 14, December 16, 1929-July 24, 1931, with notes and comments by Michael Cullinane
      J. Harbord
      H. L. Stimson
      Senator Hawes
      F. LeJ. Parker (Chief of Bureau Internal Affairs)
      P. J. Hurley (Secretary of War)
      V. Bunuan (much)
      M. Roxas
      John Switzer (New York) re: immigration of Filipinos
      Many Senators and Representatives of U.S. Congress re: Philippine Independence bills, etc.
      Oscar Sutro (California) a 13 page letter to Quezon (Nov. 6, 1930) re: Philippine independence issue, etc.
      Sumulong, Roxas, Briones, Guevara, Osias (Washington) to Quezon, Osmeña, Alas (Manila) (during May, 1930) re: mostly Hawes-Cutting Bill
      J. Laurel
      Representative Jose G. Sanvictores (Agusan-Bukidnon)
      Jake Rosenthal (Rosenthal, Inc.--the Rosenthal Shoe Distributor) --a"weekly letter" both informative and interesting and witty re: events especially in Manila to Quezon with "he is recuperating in California (mostly 1931)
      S. Osmeña, esp.:
      Osmeña to Quezon. 5 page letter (Dec. 21, 1929) re: final settlement in Philippine Legislature of a meeting between M. Kalaw and Aguinaldo--Osmeña concerned about keeping Aguinaldo on their side --also re: Gabaldon's efforts to get Agoncillo to come over to his side, again Osmeña concerned
      Osmeña to Quezon. 3 page letter (Dec. 29, 1929) re: a speech he gave in Cebu and support for them there
      Osmeña to Quezon. 2 page letter (Dec. 28, 1929) re: plans for "Junta Consoltina" (Advisory Council)
      Quezon to Osmeña. Letter (Jan.4, 1930) Quezon very sick, advises Osmeña to carry out appointments to "Junta" on his own
      Osmeña to Quezon. 4 page letter (Jan. 15, 1930) re: problems facing "Junta" especially with Democratas
      Osmeña to Quezon. 3 page letter (Jan. 17, 1930) re: more of same ("Advisory Council")
      Quezon to Osmeña. Letter (Jan. 20, 1930) re: same above
      Osmeña to Quezon. 3 page letter (Jan. 25, 1930) re: Advisory Council negotiations, Osmeña trying to determine what Quezon really desires, seeking certification
      Quezon, Osmeña, Alas to Roxas (Washington. Cable (July 12, 1930) "Nicholas Roosevelt has been mentioned as a candidate for Vice-Governor. Our people are strongly opposed to this appointment."
      Quezon to Governor-General Davis. Letter (July 13, 1930) re: his opposition to Roosevelt
      N. Roosevelt to President of U.S. Letter of resignation (Sept. 24, 1930) also re: his negative opinion of Filipino leaders and their exploits
      Sumulong to Tirona. Cable (July 24, 1930) re: Quezon's undermining of the Independence campaign and his position (actually a misunderstanding)
      Bunuan to Quezon. Letter (Aug. 28, 1930) re: among other things a transmitting of cables re: Quezon's statement about coming to U.S. in New York Times, which upset Sumulong
      Osmeña to Quezon (Monrovia). 5 page letter (Nov. 10, 1930) re: his legislative work in Philippines
      Quezon to Osmeña. 5 page letter (Jan. 6, 1931) re: events in U.S. and Sumulong's T. R.
      Quezon to Parker. 3 page letter (Jan. 11, 1931) re: Secretary of War's appointments in Philippines
      J. Laurel to Quezon. Letter (March 20, 1931) re: mostly Tayabas election problems, esp. Laurel vs. Recto, re: also Recto's negative campaign and trickiness, Laurel exhibits much animosity toward Recto, and expresses much loyalty to Quezon
      Rector to Quezon. Letter (March 24, 1931) re: his struggle with Laurel, suggests a link with Quezon but unclear
      Quezon to Laurel. Letter (April 16, 1931) Quezon expresses his support for Laurel and tells him to use this letter but it is not a super positive letter of support as Quezon can write
      Considerable correspondence re: "Ang Bagong Katipunan"--begun allegedly by Roxas and Cumena--mostly negative and some fearful of its outcome--some hint that Governor-General quieted down Roxas' activities in this regard
    - July 25, 1931-June 29, 1932 (Reel 15)
      Highlights of roll 15, July 25, 1931-June 29, 1932, with notes and comments of Michael Cullinane
      F. McIntyre, J. Harbord--continuing correspondence
      J. Switzer
      William Montavan (Director, Legal Department, National Catholic Welfare Conference)
      Senator H. Hawes, esp. 7 page letter, Aguinaldo to H. Hawes (July 25, 1931) re: independence issue
      C. Osias and P. Guevara (Resid. Comms.--heavy official correspondence re: independence or autonomy issue, Osias often expresses his loyalty to Quezon
      Osrox (Osmeña and Roxas) mission to U.S., heavy correspondence with Quaqual (Quezon, Aquino, Alas) re: work for independence bill, i.e. HHC Bill, much of it confidential
      Vicente Madrigal and Amande Avanlena (Nec. Ollid, President, Confed. de Assoces y Plantaduces de Cana-dulce)
      Rafael Palma
      A. Hurrillenu (Judge, Zamboanga) re: independence issue
      Faustino Aguilar (Secretary of Senate) re: situation in Philippines (Manila) to Quezon (Aug. 11, 1931)
      Walter Robb (American Chamber of Commerce)
      George C. Butte (Alternative Governor-General) esp. 6 page letter (many drafts) from Quezon (Jan. 7, 1932) re: sugar planters and how they should get a bigger piece of the pie, more for small guy
      Maximo Kalaw, esp. M. Kalaw to Quezon. Letter (Oct. 5, 1931) re: new Filipino mood toward independence